<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2019-08-16T23:30:44+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Maher Malaeb</title><subtitle>&quot;Best Jekyll Theme by a Mile&quot;. **Hydejack** is your presence on the web, featuring a blog, portfolio, and resume.
</subtitle><author><name>Maher Malaeb</name><email>m.n.malaeb@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of ”Coders”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hydejack/2019-08-10-brief-hisotry-of-coders/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of &quot;Coders&quot;" /><published>2019-08-10T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-08-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hydejack/brief-hisotry-of-coders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hydejack/2019-08-10-brief-hisotry-of-coders/">&lt;p&gt;Coders, who they are, and what they do changed a lot through out their short history which effectively started in the late 50’s. This history is explained by Clive Thompson in his book “Coders”. He split the changes into “four waves of coders” as he calls it. Those waves shaped the coders to who they are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wave-one-taming-thebeasts&quot;&gt;Wave One: Taming The Beasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first generation of coders emerged in the late 50’s and early 60’s. Back then computers were huge power hungry machines. You could only find one in university computer labs. Computers didn’t have a mouse or keyboard to interact with. Coders wrote programs on paper using low level language which are very hard to understand. The paper programs were then put in a queue to be handled by special personnel that punched them into cards. Computers only understood punch cards. You had to wait many hours to get the result of you program. If you made a mistake, a bug escaped, you need to go through the whole process again. Coding required so much patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invention of the transistor drastically changed the rules of the game and opened the door to create smaller computers that could be used by scientist who didn’t know coding. So the challenge of the time was to build an operating system that allowed those scientists to use the computers. Although coding had its challenge, in that era it was still regarded with a lower status when compared to hardware engineers. Coding jobs were mostly held by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wave-two-nightowls&quot;&gt;Wave Two: Night Owls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 60’s and early 70’s computers in universities such as MIT were used during the day by researchers for their studies. But during nights, the machines sat idle. So they attracted a new type of coders. Those coders came curious to learn what those machines can do and got hooked. They started tinkering with them. This opened the door for the creative usage of computers. They began using those computers to develop visual interfaces for simple games and to make music among other usages. It was the phase that introduced art into coding. It was also those coders who initiated the hacker culture. The culture of sharing code among other coders for free. The culture that accepted code regardless of whom it is coming from, be it kids, college dropouts or whoever. Code was code and that what mattered. Unfortunately, those coders were mostly boys and hacking computers overnights in computer labs creating an unwelcoming atmosphere for interested women. So this generation of coders were the first to start pushing women away from the coding field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wave-three-gettingpersonal&quot;&gt;Wave Three: Getting Personal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal Computers started to become a reality in the late 70’s but mainly in the 80’s. A middle-class family could afford to get their teenage child a computer of that time. Those personal computers became popular among teenagers because it allowed them to write their own video games and remake some of their famous arcade games. This was particularly appealing to boys which pushed girls even more away from this field. The dominance of personal computers was combined with the popularizing of the BASIC programming language. The English-like language was relatively easy to understand and came with sample programs and games that allowed those teenage boys to code their own versions of games and their own programs in their parents basements. Coding at that time was not thought of as a career or profession. Learning was done out of curiosity and for fun. The fact that everyone now have the possibility to code created a need for sharing that code to be customized and modified by other coders and re-shared again over the basic networks of the time. This was the first generation open source model.
But in the early 90’s the availability of the more advanced networks which are closer to the internet as we know it today, changed the rules of the game on how coding was done. Before the internet, programs were shipped mostly physically using floppy disks. An escaped bug was so costly to correct and took a lot of time for the fix to reach the user. Programs were carefully designed, developed and then tested in a long traditional process which was called the waterfall approach. However the internet allowed changes to the code of a program to be instantly reflected to the users. Coders now can publish a basic version of their product to the users. The users will effectively be testers of this product that will report the bugs they will see which will be resolved in a much shorter time and released over the internet. This paradigm is what is known as the agile way of building software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wave-four-take-over-theworld&quot;&gt;Wave Four: Take Over The World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web era we are living in today started to take over in the mid 90’s. With it, coding started to get more mainstream. The Netscape browser of the 90’s introduced the “view source” feature which allowed users to view the HTML code of any webpage and edit it to their likes. So code was available for everyone. The web also allowed the emerging of products such as social networks which billions of people used. Scaling introduced 2 extremely different types of problems. A technical problem of how to scale a product to be used by the whole world, in all time zones with relatively zero down time. Coders became increasingly interested not only on how to develop a program, but how to allow billions of users to use it at the same time. Those are two separate technical concerns.
The second problem is a social one. A problem which is extremely outside the area of expertise of coders. The usage of such programs at scale and psychological tricks the coders implemented in their products to get users hooked proved to impact the psychology of users sometimes in destructive ways. Abusive behavior, hate speech and some other forms of social and psychological problems emerged. Coders didn’t always have the knowledge and the incentives to deal with such consequences. What mattered was scaling up which meant more success, more control and eventually more money. When software products became at that scale, and software engineering as a career was well formulated, it started attracting a genre of new graduates that were interested in the field for the sake of power and money. Those same people who used to go to Wall Street before, found in the coding industry a new opportunity to reach their goals, especially after the 2008 financial crisis and the damaged it brought to Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this article, then you will definitely like the book “Coders: The Making of a New Tribe and the Remaking of the World” by Clive Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Maher Malaeb</name><email>m.n.malaeb@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Coders, who they are, and what they do changed a lot through out their short history which effectively started in the late 50’s. This history is explained by Clive Thompson in his book “Coders”. He split the changes into “four waves of coders” as he calls it. Those waves shaped the coders to who they are today. Wave One: Taming The Beasts The first generation of coders emerged in the late 50’s and early 60’s. Back then computers were huge power hungry machines. You could only find one in university computer labs. Computers didn’t have a mouse or keyboard to interact with. Coders wrote programs on paper using low level language which are very hard to understand. The paper programs were then put in a queue to be handled by special personnel that punched them into cards. Computers only understood punch cards. You had to wait many hours to get the result of you program. If you made a mistake, a bug escaped, you need to go through the whole process again. Coding required so much patience. The invention of the transistor drastically changed the rules of the game and opened the door to create smaller computers that could be used by scientist who didn’t know coding. So the challenge of the time was to build an operating system that allowed those scientists to use the computers. Although coding had its challenge, in that era it was still regarded with a lower status when compared to hardware engineers. Coding jobs were mostly held by women. Wave Two: Night Owls In the 60’s and early 70’s computers in universities such as MIT were used during the day by researchers for their studies. But during nights, the machines sat idle. So they attracted a new type of coders. Those coders came curious to learn what those machines can do and got hooked. They started tinkering with them. This opened the door for the creative usage of computers. They began using those computers to develop visual interfaces for simple games and to make music among other usages. It was the phase that introduced art into coding. It was also those coders who initiated the hacker culture. The culture of sharing code among other coders for free. The culture that accepted code regardless of whom it is coming from, be it kids, college dropouts or whoever. Code was code and that what mattered. Unfortunately, those coders were mostly boys and hacking computers overnights in computer labs creating an unwelcoming atmosphere for interested women. So this generation of coders were the first to start pushing women away from the coding field. Wave Three: Getting Personal Personal Computers started to become a reality in the late 70’s but mainly in the 80’s. A middle-class family could afford to get their teenage child a computer of that time. Those personal computers became popular among teenagers because it allowed them to write their own video games and remake some of their famous arcade games. This was particularly appealing to boys which pushed girls even more away from this field. The dominance of personal computers was combined with the popularizing of the BASIC programming language. The English-like language was relatively easy to understand and came with sample programs and games that allowed those teenage boys to code their own versions of games and their own programs in their parents basements. Coding at that time was not thought of as a career or profession. Learning was done out of curiosity and for fun. The fact that everyone now have the possibility to code created a need for sharing that code to be customized and modified by other coders and re-shared again over the basic networks of the time. This was the first generation open source model. But in the early 90’s the availability of the more advanced networks which are closer to the internet as we know it today, changed the rules of the game on how coding was done. Before the internet, programs were shipped mostly physically using floppy disks. An escaped bug was so costly to correct and took a lot of time for the fix to reach the user. Programs were carefully designed, developed and then tested in a long traditional process which was called the waterfall approach. However the internet allowed changes to the code of a program to be instantly reflected to the users. Coders now can publish a basic version of their product to the users. The users will effectively be testers of this product that will report the bugs they will see which will be resolved in a much shorter time and released over the internet. This paradigm is what is known as the agile way of building software. Wave Four: Take Over The World The web era we are living in today started to take over in the mid 90’s. With it, coding started to get more mainstream. The Netscape browser of the 90’s introduced the “view source” feature which allowed users to view the HTML code of any webpage and edit it to their likes. So code was available for everyone. The web also allowed the emerging of products such as social networks which billions of people used. Scaling introduced 2 extremely different types of problems. A technical problem of how to scale a product to be used by the whole world, in all time zones with relatively zero down time. Coders became increasingly interested not only on how to develop a program, but how to allow billions of users to use it at the same time. Those are two separate technical concerns. The second problem is a social one. A problem which is extremely outside the area of expertise of coders. The usage of such programs at scale and psychological tricks the coders implemented in their products to get users hooked proved to impact the psychology of users sometimes in destructive ways. Abusive behavior, hate speech and some other forms of social and psychological problems emerged. Coders didn’t always have the knowledge and the incentives to deal with such consequences. What mattered was scaling up which meant more success, more control and eventually more money. When software products became at that scale, and software engineering as a career was well formulated, it started attracting a genre of new graduates that were interested in the field for the sake of power and money. Those same people who used to go to Wall Street before, found in the coding industry a new opportunity to reach their goals, especially after the 2008 financial crisis and the damaged it brought to Wall Street. If you liked this article, then you will definitely like the book “Coders: The Making of a New Tribe and the Remaking of the World” by Clive Thompson.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/brief_history_of_coders-min.jpg" /></entry></feed>